<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>devops on Serhii Vasylenko</title>
    <link>https://serhii.vasylenko.info/tags/devops/</link>
    <description>Recent content in devops on Serhii Vasylenko</description>
    <image>
      <url>https://serhii.vasylenko.info/assets/img/website-logo-open-graph.jpeg</url>
      <link>https://serhii.vasylenko.info/assets/img/website-logo-open-graph.jpeg</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://serhii.vasylenko.info/tags/devops/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Manage Ansible playbook secrets with AWS services</title>
      <link>https://serhii.vasylenko.info/2020/08/06/ansible-secrets-aws-ssm-sm.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://serhii.vasylenko.info/2020/08/06/ansible-secrets-aws-ssm-sm.html</guid>
      <description>A better way to store sensitive information for Ansible on EC2 or other services</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Lookup plugins for Ansible allow you to do a lot of cool things. One of them is to securely pass sensitive information to your playbooks.
If you manage some apps in AWS with Ansible, then using Parameter Store or Secrets Manager along with it might greatly improve your security.</p>
<h2 id="variables-with-ssm-parameter-store">Variables with SSM Parameter Store</h2>
<p>Let&rsquo;s say you have some variables defined in &lsquo;defaults/main.yaml&rsquo; file of your role or maybe in group_vars.yaml file.</p>
<div class="highlight"><div style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4">
<table style="border-spacing:0;padding:0;margin:0;border:0;width:auto;overflow:auto;display:block;"><tr><td style="vertical-align:top;padding:0;margin:0;border:0;">
<pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f">1
</span><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f">2
</span><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f">3
</span><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f">4
</span><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f">5
</span><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f">6
</span></code></pre></td>
<td style="vertical-align:top;padding:0;margin:0;border:0;;width:100%">
<pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-yaml" data-lang="yaml">---
<span style="color:#75715e"># content of dev.vars.yaml to be included in your play or role</span>
<span style="color:#f92672">use_tls</span>: <span style="color:#66d9ef">true</span>
<span style="color:#f92672">application_port</span>: <span style="color:#ae81ff">3000</span>
<span style="color:#f92672">app_env</span>: <span style="color:#ae81ff">development</span>
<span style="color:#f92672">stripe_api_key</span>: <span style="color:#ae81ff">1HGASU2eZvKYlo2CT5MEcnC39HqLyjWD</span>
</code></pre></td></tr></table>
</div>
</div><p>If you store such things locally on Ansible control node, you probably encrypt it with <a href="https://docs.ansible.com/ansible/latest/user_guide/vault.html">ansible-vault</a></p>
<p>SSM Parameter Store gives you more flexibility and security by centralized storage and management of parameters and secrets, so let&rsquo;s use it with Ansible:</p>
<div class="highlight"><div style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4">
<table style="border-spacing:0;padding:0;margin:0;border:0;width:auto;overflow:auto;display:block;"><tr><td style="vertical-align:top;padding:0;margin:0;border:0;">
<pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f">1
</span><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f">2
</span><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f">3
</span><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f">4
</span><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f">5
</span><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f">6
</span></code></pre></td>
<td style="vertical-align:top;padding:0;margin:0;border:0;;width:100%">
<pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-yaml" data-lang="yaml"><span style="color:#75715e"># content of dev.vars.yaml to be included in your play or role</span>

<span style="color:#f92672">use_tls</span>: <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;{{lookup(&#39;aws_ssm&#39;, &#39;/dev/webserver/use_tls&#39;)}}&#34;</span>
<span style="color:#f92672">application_port</span>: <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;{{lookup(&#39;aws_ssm&#39;, &#39;/dev/webserver/application_port&#39;)}}&#34;</span>
<span style="color:#f92672">app_env</span>: <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;{{lookup(&#39;aws_ssm&#39;, &#39;/dev/webserver/app_env&#39;)}}&#34;</span>
<span style="color:#f92672">stripe_api_key</span>: <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;{{lookup(&#39;aws_ssm&#39;, &#39;/dev/webserver/stripe_api_key&#39;)}}&#34;</span>
</code></pre></td></tr></table>
</div>
</div><p>The syntax is fairly simple:</p>
<p>The <code>aws_ssm</code> argument – is the name of plugin.</p>
<p>The <code>/dev/webserver/use_tls</code> argument – is the path to the key in Paramter Store.</p>
<p>Surely you can do the same for a group of servers with group variables, for example:</p>
<p>You can use this anywhere you can use templating: in a play, in variables file, or a Jinja2 template.</p>
<h2 id="variables-with-secret-manager">Variables with Secret Manager</h2>
<p>Another cool lookup plugin is Secrets Manager. In a nutshell, it has the same kind of functionality but it uses JSON format by feault.</p>
<p>Here is a quick example of its functionality in a Playbook:</p>
<div class="highlight"><div style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4">
<table style="border-spacing:0;padding:0;margin:0;border:0;width:auto;overflow:auto;display:block;"><tr><td style="vertical-align:top;padding:0;margin:0;border:0;">
<pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f">1
</span><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f">2
</span><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f">3
</span><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f">4
</span></code></pre></td>
<td style="vertical-align:top;padding:0;margin:0;border:0;;width:100%">
<pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-yaml" data-lang="yaml">---
- <span style="color:#f92672">name</span>: <span style="color:#ae81ff">Extract something secrets from Secret Manager</span>
  <span style="color:#f92672">debug</span>:
    <span style="color:#f92672">msg</span>: <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;{{ lookup(&#39;aws_secret&#39;, &#39;dev/some-secrets&#39;)}}&#34;</span>
</code></pre></td></tr></table>
</div>
</div><p>The above task will generate the following output</p>
<div class="highlight"><div style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4">
<table style="border-spacing:0;padding:0;margin:0;border:0;width:auto;overflow:auto;display:block;"><tr><td style="vertical-align:top;padding:0;margin:0;border:0;">
<pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f"> 1
</span><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f"> 2
</span><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f"> 3
</span><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f"> 4
</span><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f"> 5
</span><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f"> 6
</span><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f"> 7
</span><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f"> 8
</span><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f"> 9
</span><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f">10
</span><span style="margin-right:0.4em;padding:0 0.4em 0 0.4em;color:#7f7f7f">11
</span></code></pre></td>
<td style="vertical-align:top;padding:0;margin:0;border:0;;width:100%">
<pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell">TASK <span style="color:#f92672">[</span>Extract something secrets from Secret Manager<span style="color:#f92672">]</span> ****************************************************
ok: <span style="color:#f92672">[</span>some_server<span style="color:#f92672">]</span> <span style="color:#f92672">=</span>&gt; <span style="color:#f92672">{</span>
    <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;msg&#34;</span>: <span style="color:#f92672">{</span>
        <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;dbname&#34;</span>: <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;database&#34;</span>,
        <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;engine&#34;</span>: <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;mysql&#34;</span>,
        <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;host&#34;</span>: <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;127.0.0.1&#34;</span>,
        <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;password&#34;</span>: <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;password&#34;</span>,
        <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;port&#34;</span>: <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;3306&#34;</span>,
        <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;username&#34;</span>: <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;db_user&#34;</span>
    <span style="color:#f92672">}</span>
<span style="color:#f92672">}</span>
</code></pre></td></tr></table>
</div>
</div><p>This is nice if you want to insert a JSON as is, but you will need additional parsing in case you want to get only some of JSON elements.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>If you’re using Ansible in CI/CD, then having it on an EC2 Instance with the IAM role will make you avoid keeping any secrets on that instance at all.<br>
The IAM role must allow at least the read access to SSM Parameter Store (+ KMS read access to be able to decrypt the keys) or the read access to Secrets Manager.</p>
<p>You can find documentation for described plugins here <a href="https://docs.ansible.com/ansible/latest/plugins/lookup/aws_ssm.html">aws_ssm</a> and here <a href="https://docs.ansible.com/ansible/latest/plugins/lookup/aws_secret.html">aws_secret</a>.</p>
<p>More about lookup plugins: <a href="https://docs.ansible.com/ansible/latest/plugins/lookup.html">https://docs.ansible.com/ansible/latest/plugins/lookup.html</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DevOps team in outsource. A team?</title>
      <link>https://serhii.vasylenko.info/2020/03/20/devops-team-in-outsource-a-team.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://serhii.vasylenko.info/2020/03/20/devops-team-in-outsource-a-team.html</guid>
      <description>This article was written a long time ago in a galaxy far, far away...</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am a team lead in an outsourcing company. That means I believe <em>(or convince myself)</em> that I lead the team <em>(wait, wait, there will be even more obvious discoveries)</em>.</p>
<p>I am sure that <strong>a team</strong> can achieve more than a single person or a group. And the story I want to tell is about making the team from a group of people with personal and non-connected tasks. I assume this is going to be a series of posts, and hopefully, I will add a table of contents here.</p>
<h3 id="a-group-or-a-team">A group or a team?</h3>
<p>It is quite rare to find a project that involves more than 10-15 people in a small or mid-size outsourcing company. With such project size, a single DevOps engineer is enough to handle the whole job. Or an engineer may work on several projects at the same time if projects are relatively small. This is because the scope of work to be done fits into the schedule of a single person. So it is either one-to-one or one-to-many connection in most cases: either the employee works with one project or the employee works with several projects simultaneously.</p>
<p>Outsourcing a &ldquo;DevOps&rdquo; within this context usually means assigning an individual for the work with a client or/and a client&rsquo;s team.</p>
<p>Now imagine: you have several people in a room, all of them are DevOps engineers working in the same outsource company and all they work with their &ldquo;own&rdquo; projects separately.</p>
<p><strong>So would you call that group of people &ldquo;a team&rdquo;?</strong></p>
<p>Wikipedia states that &ldquo;a team&rdquo; is a group of individuals (human or non-human) working together to achieve <strong>their [common] goal</strong>.
As well as common sense tells us that &ldquo;a team&rdquo; is something that groups people to make them work for a <strong>mutual outcome</strong>.</p>
<p>And here comes an obvious but a difficult question: what common goal(s) a group of people can have whereas each member of that group has its own goal, which is not related to others'? A bit contradictory, isn&rsquo;t it?</p>
<h3 id="a-goal">A Goal</h3>
<p>Conventional thinking tells us that a goal for the for-profit company is to make money. This is true, and I don&rsquo;t want to argue with it. Therefore, does it mean that a goal for a team of engineers inside the company is the same as for the company as a whole?</p>
<p>Yes&hellip; Yet, not only, or almost.</p>
<p>Yes, because it&rsquo;s the main reason why we work for an outsourcing company. We do the job for clients, clients pay the company, the company pays us.</p>
<p>However, there is a long chain of events and processes that leads from the start of a contract to the paid invoice. A team of engineers is the inalienable part of that chain, with a focus on its work - deliver technical solutions following the client&rsquo;s expectations and requirements.</p>
<p>This conclusion reveals the goal for the DevOps team in the outsourcing company: grow the quality of work by a process of ongoing improvement and refinement of technical and soft skills. So simple, so obvious.</p>
<p>And this goal means nothing by itself. But to sustain it and adapt, to make it desirable for the team, and to make it a team&rsquo;s foundation eventually, we need the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>Values</li>
<li>Principles</li>
<li>Common interests</li>
</ul>
<p>One of the crucial responsibilities of a team lead is to foster these three pillars of a team.</p>
<p>The <strong>VALUES</strong>  is something that lets us feel comfortable with the people surrounding us in the office. The list of values is not carved in stone, it can (and eventually should) change as the team evolves. But here is the most constant items for my team:</p>
<ul>
<li>openness in communication</li>
<li>respect to each other&rsquo;s opinion</li>
<li>empathy</li>
<li>feeling free to provide critic and being ready to receive it</li>
<li>count on help from a teammate and be ready to help</li>
<li>ability to work remotely and have flexible working hours</li>
</ul>
<p>The <strong>PRINCIPLES</strong> is a set of beliefs and policies that keeps us on the required level of productivity and disciplines us, and stimulates the longing to improve. Again, this list can be and should be adjusted as the time goes and the team evolves, but here is the most up to date for us:</p>
<ul>
<li>we learn constantly</li>
<li>we are the first who appraises the quality of our work</li>
<li>we are proactive</li>
<li>we are open: if we do not agree with something or something is worrying us, we should be brave enough to say it</li>
<li>we may defend own point of view, but be ready to accept that it is incorrect</li>
<li>we can make mistakes, but we must learn from it and do not repeat them</li>
<li>we must help our teammates</li>
<li>we keep our promises</li>
</ul>
<p>The <strong>COMMON INTERESTS</strong> is more about informal things we share within a team. This includes (but not limited to) team building events, discussions and arguments about new technologies, so-called water-cooler chats, and so on. Being less formal, this pillar acts as a glue for the team. This is because we are all humans, first of all, and we generally work for 1/3 of our day (not including weekends), so we need to stay humans at work as well. I mean it is impossible to switch off the &lsquo;human&rsquo; for that 1/3 of the day, leaving only the engineer for this time. Hence, this must be admitted and we must cope with it by putting several informal things into formal work.</p>
<p>These pillars create a team culture where learning, creativity, and an open mindset are encouraged.</p>
<h3 id="the-team">The Team</h3>
<p>This is how a group of people with separate goals may become a team. While we do not have a goal (&ldquo;one for all&rdquo;) that is measurable or has a fixed point of completion, we still have a common aim whose realization is based on pillars of teamwork. And with a set of sub-goals, this may be a specific, achievable (until you find something else to improve, which should happen quite often) and even realistic. So it&rsquo;s kinda 60% S.M.A.R.T. goal :smile:</p>
<p>Unfortunately or fortunately (if you like your team lead job) there is a lot of work that needs to be done and a lot of questions need to be answered to implement the described approach:</p>
<ul>
<li>How to translate own values to the team and create the new ones together?</li>
<li>How to make people communicate in such a team and share their knowledge?</li>
<li>How to define who does what?</li>
<li>How to teach team members to learn?</li>
<li>How to keep team members loyal to the team and company?</li>
<li>How to mitigate conflicts and how to use them?</li>
<li>How to keep team members motivated when the work becomes boring and the level of engagement goes down?</li>
<li>and much much more</li>
</ul>
<p>I wish I could answer all these questions at once, and I wish there were only correct answers.
But my experience tells me that it is possible to answer them one by one. And I hope to share that here someday!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
